<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<books>
    <book ID="MartialForms" Title="{{M|The Paths of The Contenders}}">

        <page>

{{yellow|Introduction:}}

I've decided to document the teachings that were passed down to me by The Amethyst Shell. For fear this path, which she used to ripen and tame my wild soul, might vanish into the annals of time and lose its chance to enlighten another.

        </page>

        <page>
{{M|The Path of the Dawnglider.}}

I find it wise to begin with the form I personally heralded.

Like the majestic creature it is named from, this form is a jack of all trades: training one to take advantage of every limb, to take a forward tussle without fear, to attack with the ferociousness and cunning of a dawnglider. The Amethyst Shell noted this particular stance excelled as a solid middle-ground while remaining in neutral to your opponent, though there are better options—this remains a keen choice no matter the situation during a struggle.

Of course, the true genius of this stance is its ability to adapt other stances' key traits into its own, a secret I personally developed. You see, with every form you learn, this kata proves to adopt and take advantage of certain aspects of the new forms' abilities at its' basics, improving this form bit by bit with each.

Like per-say, you happen to master the Path of the Salthopper? You can take advantage of its innate damage against ailed foes while, adapting its sharp-strikes periodically.
        </page>
        <page>
It would be wrong for me to continue without noting, of course, its most pertinent secret. Those who train in the Contenders' Way, will note a change within the body, particularly in reaction to ingesting the warm-drought. This great power delivers to us unbridled abilities, and when used carefully can save one in a pinch.

Yes, the warm-drought unleashes a truly frightening power, the true reason it is called the dawnglider's form. The wine swells into a fire in the stomach, unleashing itself in haphazard eructations. It isn't wise to evoke this unless you are sure you are going to need it. Otherwise, you may want to stay far away from tap-houses.
        </page>
        <page>
{{M|The Path of the Astral Cabby.}}

There is something to be said of the creator of this this method of fighting. “Naz'il Ek'do,” was said to have created this form in a fringe moment, deep beneath ruined derelicts beyond the river Elm, when surrounded by mirror-shard bugs and juice-maddened sappers. By legend, in a sudden fit of genius, he began to sway and shift like a prowling feline, adopting an almost rhythmic, serpentine pattern to his footwork that hypnotized and disgruntled his foes. Naz'il, after supposedly surviving this incident would master the form, discovering the strange movement wasn't unlike an Astral Tabby's prowling. It would latter be discovered the movements were ideal for avoiding projectile fire due to its erratic and unpredictable nature.

Though the Amethyst Shell's lack of mobility made it nigh-impossible for her to truly utilize this form to its maximum, tales of those who have perfected its uses still circulate through fables of the contenders and she fully acknowledges this form as a proper option in neutral situations as the evasive tendencies let its practitioner both engage and disengage safely from your enemy. It is unknown if the warming-drought has any true effect on this particular stance.
        </page>
        <page>
{{W|The Path of the Salthopper}}

Sometimes laying down percussive strikes and careful take-downs isn't enough. Some enemies are highly armored, requiring more precise methods to break them down, something this path intends to provide. Through precise blows delivered using the 'scythe-hand' strike, one can target sensitive area's of the body, hobbling, and even disrupting the psionic lay-lines of their enemies' minds. The various techniques used in this style allow it to leave foes incapable of fighting back, however—the strikes implemented do little in the way of physically maiming or fatally harming your foe. Often, practitioners of this style will switch between other forms after having dismantled their foe with this one.

The Amethyst Shell once said this kata is integral for fighters who intend to take advantage of multiple forms; by stunning, and grounding your enemies, you give yourself time to access other stances or options in battle in a moments notice.
        </page>
        <page>
Of course, as with any form related to the contenders' way, with the warming-drought, one might unlock a secret genius in this form. With wine, the drought fuels explosive movement, allowing one to leap great distances—or, as they say, 'jump high.'
        </page>
        <page>
{{w|The Path of the Saltback}}
        
Brought to fruition by the Amethyst Shell herself, this was said to be the first form of the contenders, idealized with the intent to teach one the power of a strong defense. Through physical conditioning and careful training, this form focused one to deflect or redirect their enemies' opposing energy safely away from the practitioner, or even back at their foe. The goal is being rooted, staying as steadfast and unmovable as the great salt-back itself. Practitioners of this form often make use of gauntlets which help to deflect even the bluntest of strikes. 

However, this rootedness comes at the cost of some of your mobility, as this stance might encourage constant rigidness instead of learning to root upon impact of a blow. Therefor, it is often used as way to bring the fight to a neutral standpoint or offer a moment for a counterattack.
        </page>
        <page>
It is said that if one downs the warming-drought while under the effects of this stances' physical influence, their flesh is said to harden, rubberize, strange things that let them glance off both physical and elemental attacks for a brief-time.

        </page>
        <page>
{{r|The Path of the Slumberling}}
        

A relatively new form, though its often debated among the contenders whether the slumberling path is a true form or not. It relies heavily on placing one into a battle trance, throwing away all sense of self-preservation and replacing it with a primal, bloodthirsty rage. This path unleashes its fury in wide, arcs of sonic-fast strikes, strikes so strong they tear through foes and can even harm others around them. The severity of this stance increases ones' yield to the point they can tear a creature's limb from their being or fling heavy units away with ease, all at the cost of losing focus in terms of combat awareness. Those who follow this path are also said to have the ability to hibernate, entering a deep slumber where they regenerate wounds and restore stamina.

It should be said that despite the almost supernatural effects in regards to the warming-drought and other forms, the slumbering form remains rather tame. It Is said to aid in the metabolic regeneration of body while sleeping.
        </page>
        <page>

With this, I end with a word of caution, the contenders' have come to Qud to wreak havoc with their competitive ways. With word of an ape god who's fist is said to unrival any, or tales of treasure and fame from journeys in the hellish depths where only nightmares exist, it was only in time. The paths of the contenders was never meant to be a way of violence but as the teachings have spread, so have the influences of the different institutions within it. I was hoping my master's way would bring peace and healing to the wildness of Qud but of course, fate would not have it so. No matter, I'll have to fight to keep our ways true—and stop those who would abuse them. 

It is the most I can do in her.

In memory of the Amethyst Shell.




By The Warding-Fist Kali-Mara, Arshira.
        </page>


    </book>
</books>