<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<books>
        <book ID="MartialForms" Title="{{M|The Paths of The Contenders}}">

                <page>
“In memory of the Amethyst Shell.” - By The Warding-Fist Kali-Mara, Arshira.

I've decided to document the teachings that were passed down to me by The Amethyst  Shell, for I fear this path, which she used to ripen and tame my wild soul, might vanish into the annals of time and lose its chance to enlighten another.

Those who train in the Contenders' Way, will note a change within the body both through conditioning and honing one’s thoughtstuff.  Particularly in reaction to ingestion of the warm-drought. This great power delivers to us unbridled abilities, and when used carefully can save one in a pinch.
                </page>

                <page>
The Path of the Dawnglider.

I find it wise to begin with the form I personally mastered.

Like the majestic creature it is named after,  this form is a jack of all trades: training one to take advantage of every limb, to tussle forward without fear, to attack with the ferociousness and cunning of a dawnglider. The Amethyst Shell noted this particular stance excelled as a solid middle-ground for engaging an opponent, and although there are better options, this stance remains a keen choice no matter the situation during a struggle.

Of course, the true genius of this stance is its ability to improve alongside you: as you learn new techniques, the Form of the Dawnglider changes too, borrowing and adopting other stances’ key traits.

Let’s say you manage to master the Path of the Salthopper. The Form of the Dawnglider will change with you, allowing you to take advantage of that path’s innate damage against ailed foes without needing you to shift into the stance of the Salthopper.
                </page>

                <page>
It would be wrong for me to continue without noting, of course, its most powerful secret. 

Yes, the warm-drought unleashes a truly frightening power, the true reason why this form is named after dawngliders. The wine swells into a fire in the stomach, unleashing itself in haphazard eructations. It isn't wise to evoke this unless you are sure you are going to need it. Otherwise, you may want to stay far away from tap-houses.
                </page>

                <page>
The Path of the Salt-Back
        
Brought to fruition by the Amethyst Shell herself, this was said to be the first form of the contenders, created with the intent to teach one the power of a strong defense. Through physical conditioning and specialised training, users of this form learned to deflect or redirect their enemies' energy safely away from the practitioner, or even back at their foe. The goal is being rooted, staying as steadfast and unmovable as the great salt-back itself. Practitioners of this form often make use of gauntlets which help them to deflect even the sharpest of weapons. 

However, this stance's defensive prowess comes at the cost of some of your mobility, a  disadvantage inherent of it’s methodology. Therefore, it is often used as a way to bring the fight to a neutral standpoint or offer a moment for a counterattack.
                </page>

                <page>
The Path of the Salt-Hopper

Sometimes laying down percussive strikes and careful take-downs isn't enough. Some enemies are highly armored, requiring more delicate methods to break them down, something this path intends to provide. Through precise blows delivered using the 'scythe-hand' strike, one can target sensitive areas of the body, hobbling, and even disrupting the psionic lay-lines of their enemies' mind. The various techniques used in this style allow one to leave foes incapable of fighting back, however, the force behind these strikes do little in terms of fatally harming your  opponent. Often, practitioners of this style will switch between other forms after having dismantled their foe with this one.

The Amethyst Shell once said this kata is integral for fighters who intend to take advantage of multiple forms; by stunning, and grounding your enemies, you give yourself time to access other stances or options in battle in a moment's notice.
                </page>

                <page>
Of course, as with any form related to the Contenders’ Way, with the warming-drought, one might unlock a secret genius in this form. With wine, the drought fuels explosive movement, allowing one to leap great distances—or, as they say, 'jump good.'
                </page>

                <page>
The Path of the Astral Tabby.

There is something to be said of the creator of this this method of fighting, Naz'il Ek'do, who was said to have created this form in the heat of the moment, deep beneath ruined derelicts beyond the river Elm, when surrounded by mirror-shard bugs and juice-maddened sappers. Legend has it, in a sudden fit of genius he began to sway and shift like a prowling feline, adopting an almost rhythmic, serpentine pattern to his footwork that hypnotized and befuddled his foes. Naz'il, after supposedly surviving this incident, would master the form, discovering the strange movement wasn't unlike an Astral Tabby's prowling. It would later be discovered the movements were ideal for avoiding projectile fire due to its erratic and unpredictable nature.

Though the Amethyst Shell's lack of mobility made it nigh-impossible for her to truly utilize this form to its maximum, tales of those who have perfected its uses still circulate through fables of the contenders and she fully acknowledges its evasive techniques which let its practitioner both engage and disengage safely from your enemy.

It is unknown if the warming-drought has any true effect on this particular stance.
                </page>

                <page>
The Path of the Slumberling        

A relatively new form, and it's often debated among the contenders whether the Slumberling Path is a true form or not. It relies heavily on forcing one into a self-endangering battle trance, and though having kata's of its own, it loses any semblance of a true disciplined form due to its wild nature. Despite this, the effectiveness of this path has managed to keep its place here--much to some of the other forms’ practitioners’ chagrin. It relies heavily on placing yourself into a battle trance, throwing away all sense of self-preservation and replacing it with primal, bloodthirsty rage. This path unleashes its fury in wide arcs of sonic-fast strikes, strikes so strong they tear through foes and can even harm others around them. The s stance increases one's' yield to the point of being able to tear a creature's limb from their being or even fling heavy creatures away with ease, all at the cost of losing combat awareness. Those who follow this path are also said to have the ability to hibernate, entering a deep slumber where they regenerate wounds and restore stamina.

It should be said that the warming-drought has rather tame effects when ingested in this form, simply enhancing the metabolic regeneration of the body while slumbering.
                </page>

                <page>

I end with a word of caution: the contenders' have come to Qud to wreak havoc with their competitive ways. It was only a matter of time, with spreading rumors of an ape god, whose fist is unrivaled by any, and tales of treasure and fame that can be found in the hellish depths of Qud. There are many who would like their names etched into Contender’s leg The Paths of the Contenders were never meant to be a way of violence but as the teachings have spread, so have the influences of different institutions within it.

I was hoping my master's way would bring peace and healing to the wildness of Qud but of course, fate would not have it so. No matter, I'll have to fight to keep our ways true—and stop those who would abuse them. 

It is the most I can do for my late-master, and the only one who cherished me as family.

                </page>
        </book>
</books>